No, it doesn't
没有啊
There's no sound there
还是没有声音啊
You have to be in tune with it
要心有灵犀才听得到
You know?
知道吗？
Silly...
呆子
October 14th, 2006
二六年十月十四日
Changbing... The sound of a windbreak forest
长滨，防风林声
October 24th, 2006
二六年十月二十四日
I've found it
我找到了
October 16th, 2006
二六年十月十六日
Chenggong... The sound of a fish auction
成功，鱼市场拍卖声
October 26th, 2006
二六年十月二十六日
Chenggong... Site of the fish auction
成功鱼市拍卖场
I've found it
我找到了
Madam
老板娘
Hey
嘿
Sorry to bother you
不好意思想麻烦你
Please listen to this sound
听听看这个声音
Listen to what?
听什么的？
It's a tape
是个录音带
Have a listen to see if you know where it is
然后你听听看知不知道是在哪里
They're aboriginal people
这是原住民嘛
They sound like old folk and children
阿公阿嬷还有小朋友在吵…
There are so many windbreak forests
防风林这么多…
They sound all the same
那防风林的声音都是一样啦
But I have been to Changbing
可是我有到长滨那个地方
I think it's the same sound
我觉得是一样的声音
Miss Why are you listening to that?
小姐你听那个声音要做什么？
For no reason really
没有啦
I just want to go to...
我只是想要到这些声音
...the place where that sound comes from To feel it
发出来的地方感觉一下
Miss, why do you want to feel it?
小姐你要感觉这个要作什么呢？
Just to feel it
感觉看看啊
What's the point of that?
这么做有什么意义吗？
It's too vague
茫茫渺渺
It's impossible to find a place just its sound
你听这个声音要找地方不可能咧
Madam
老板娘
This envelope...
这个信封
Is it yours?
是不是你们这边的？
Yes, it's ours
是啊，这我们的没错
Then do you remember...
那你记不记得
...a sound recordist staying here before?
有一个录声音的人在这边住过？
A sound recordist?
录声音的人喔
Was he holding something very big...
是不是拿一支这么大支的
...like a big microphone.
大支麦克风
Very furry at the front
前面毛长长这样
I guess so
应该是
He said he came to record the...
他说要来录什么
...the sounds of Taiwan
台湾的声音啦
What kind of person was he?
他人怎么样？
He was very nice.
人很好啊
Pleasent talking, nice attitude
讲话啦，还有态度都很好
What did he look like?
外表呢？
Look like...
外表喔
He was gentle looking, thin...
外表斯斯文文、瘦瘦的
...very handsome, easy going
很英俊，人很好相处
Are you his...
你是他什么人？
Why are you asking so many questions?
怎么问他问这么多？
We are friends
朋友啦
Really?
真的吗？
If you are his friend...
如果你是他朋友
...how come you don't know what he looks like?
怎么不知道他长什么样子？
Well...
没有啦
Excuse me
抱歉喔
I'd been with Yazhu for five years
雅竺和我在一起已经五年了
From the time I graduated...
从我大学毕业
...right through my military service...
当完兵
...until I became a sound recordist
一直到我做了录音师
I thought we were meant for each other
我一直以为我们是很合适的一对
When I was with her...
和她在一起
...I felt peaceful and happy
我感到十分的宁静，幸福
I thought she felt the same way
我以为她也是一样
Maybe she did, once
也许曾经是吧
I really loved her very much
我真的很爱她
And I really needed her too
也真的很需要她
There were many things that I understood...
有很多事情
...only after we broke up
却在分手之后我才懂
Actually she broke up with me
分手是她提的
That night,
那一天晚上
as usual...
我像往常一样
...I called her before going to sleep
在睡前打电话给她
We both had jobs by then
这几个月我们各有各的工作
So we didn't meet so often
很少碰面
We were chatting away...
我们聊着聊着
...when she suddenly said...
她突然跟我说
"Don't you think
你不觉得
we both need a change?"
我们都需要改变了吗？
I thought she was kidding
我以为她是在开玩笑
So I tried to laugh it off
就嘻嘻哈哈的应了她几句
But she went on...
可是她又接着说
"I want to break up with you"
我想和你分手
"I'm serious"
我是认真的
Yazhu really wanted to stop seeing me
雅竺真的想要和我分开了
She wasn'tjoking
她不是开玩笑的
I'd always thought our world was stable
我一直以为我们的世界 是这个样子的
With her...
有她在
...I could take
我可以挺身去面对所有生活上
all the pressures
工作上的压力
Difficulties...
困境
Setbacks...
挫折
Depressions
沮丧
Even pains
甚至是苦痛
Because I knew...
因为我知道
...with her understanding...
只要有她懂我
...just her being there...
只要有她在
...she'd support me
她会一直支持我
She'd believe in me
相信我
She'd give me strength
给我力量
And that would be enough
这样就够了
Since the break-up,
和她分手之后
my life has been a mess
我的日子就这样乱七八糟地过着
Why can't I remember
为什么我没有办法回想起
all the details?
所有的细节啊
I'm thinking of the months before...
我想起我们分手前那几个月
...I couldn't accept...
我没有办法接受
...that we'd seen
那就是我们最后一次
our last movie together
一起去看电影
...for the last time
一起相拥入眠
That we'd had a meal together...
那是我们最后一次
There were so many things we hadn't yet done together
我们还有好多事情没有一起做啊
We hadn't been abroad together
我们还没有一起出国去玩啊
We hadn't seen snow together
我们还没有一起去看雪啊
We hadn't made
我们还没有一起完成
"Sounds of Formosa" together
福尔摩沙之音啊
Now you are Yazhu
现在你是雅竺
I am you
我是你
I expected...
我以为
...to feel sad...
分手了
...after the break-up
会难过
I'd be heart-broken
会心痛
But I thought...
我以为
...after the pain...
痛过了
...life would go on
日子还是会继续过下去
My life would still move forward
我的人生还是会继续往前走
I've realized only slowly...
可是我却慢慢发现
...that since you left me...
不知道该怎么活下去
...I don't know how to go on living...
自从我的生命
...without you
没有了你
You have to be strong
你要坚强一点啊
You know?
知道吗
Silly...
呆子
I'm also on my own
我现在也是一个人啊
I have to take care of myself too
我也是自己在照顾自己
If you truly love me...
如果你真的爱我的话
...you have to remember what I told you
你要记得我跟你说过的话
Be good
要好好的
Don't make me worry
不要让我担心
Don't make me sad
不要让我难过
You got that?
知道吗？
I will
我会…
I'll be good
我会好好的
"Girl, your boyfriends..."
妹妹的男朋友
"...are all leading lights"
完全都是男主角
"Ugly guys like us..."
像我们这么丑的男人
"...don't deserve your love"
哪有资格爱上你
"There's no place for me in your dreams"
妹妹的理想没有我的存在
"It drives me to drink every day!"
哎呀害我天天马拉桑（喝醉）
"My dearest girl..."
我最亲爱的好妹妹
"...goodbye from the bottom of my heart"
我最亲爱的莎哟哪啦
"How can I forget you?"
叫我怎么能够忘记你
"Grandpa, Grandma..."
欧里桑呀欧巴桑
"What am I to do?"
我该怎么办
"How will I ever forget her?"
叫我怎么能够忘记她
Miss!
小姐
Sing with us!
一起唱嘛
I can't sing
我不会唱耶
It doesn't matter
没关系啦
Just let it out
声音拿出来就对了
"If you don't believe..."
如果你不相信
"...God knows"
天知道地知道
"Believe it or not..."
信不信由你
What's your name?
什么名字呢？
Ruoyun
小云
"Ruoyun, Ruoyun..."
小云呀小云呀
"There's no true love"
没有真的爱
Open your mind!
放开心胸嘛
Okay
好
Just sing along, alright?
唱吧，好不好？
Then, when I sing...
接下来我唱的时候
...you follow
你跟着啊
Okay
好
Go for it
加油
Ruoyun!
小云
Now you can sing!
会唱了嘛
Take care!
小心喔
Goodbye!
再见
Hey...
喂
What about you?
那你呢？
What happened between you and your wife?
你跟你老婆发生了什么事啊？
And what's that wedding invitation in your hand all about?
你手上那张喜帖 是不是有什么故事啊
The girl I liked in college got married here
我大学时候 喜欢的女生嫁来这里
So you came for a wedding in Taidong
原来你是来台东喝喜酒的啊
Hey...
喂
This was three years ago
这是三年前耶
I didn't go to her wedding three years ago
三年前我没有来参加她的婚礼
So you're three years late
你三年后再来
The wedding's probably over by now
婚礼应该已经结束了吧
It was only after she got married...
她结婚以后
...that I started to miss her
我反而开始想念她
I've been wondering whether or not...
我常在想
...she's been happy since then
不知道她这几年过得幸不幸福
I haven't seen her in ten years
我们已经有十年没有见面了
Surely it hasn't taken you ten years...
该不会十年后才发现
...to find out she's your real soulmate?
她才是你真正的灵魂伴侣吧
Very possibly
有可能
But she's already married
不过她已经嫁人了
So even you shrinks
怎么你们心理医生
have shitty storylines!
也会上演这种烂戏码
Shitty storylines indeed
真的是烂戏码
Gensheng Road... 577
更生路五百七十七号
What number is it?
上面是写几号？
We're there
到了
How can that be?
怎么会这样？
Where's 591?
五百九十一呢？
Sir...
欧里桑
Excuse me
不好意思，请问一下
Where's 591, Gensheng Road?
更生路五百九十一号在哪？
591?
五百九十一号喔
You're in 589 here...
你们这边是五百八十九
...but that's 595 over there
但是再过去那边 就是五百九十五了
Why is there no 591?
那怎么没有五百九十一号
Well...
这个喔
Some houses were demolished a while back
几年前这些房子被拆过
It's an alley now
现在变成巷子了
So you might not find it
所以你来可能会找不到
Oh, I see
这样呀
So there's no longer a 591
所以这里已经没有 五百九十一号了
That's right
没有
Do you know of a woman
那你知不知道差不多三年前
who got married there three years ago?
有一个女孩子嫁来这附近
Was there?
有吗？
In her thirties
差不多三十几岁
160 cm tall
一百六十公分高
Good-looking
长得很清秀
Light-skinned and thin
白白的，瘦瘦的…
I really don't know
这我就不知道了
No-one comes to mind
没有印象
You're sure it was in Taidong?
你确定她有嫁到台东来吗？
You go ahead
你赶路吧
Then take care of yourself
那你保重
Bye bye
拜拜
I want to talk to you so much
好想跟你说话
So why couldn't I do it?
可是为什么没有办法
Why can't you care more about me?
为什么就不能多关心我一点
Why don't you ever know
为什么你从来都不知道
what I need?
我需要的是什么
I'm so tired
我好累
Do you know...
你知道吗
However much physical contact we have...
再怎么样身体的亲密接触
...it doesn't fill the emptiness in my heart
都没有办法弥补 我心中的那个空缺
We never really get to where
我们已经没有办法
I want to go
一起到达我想要到的地方
Now I'm sitting by the sea
现在我坐在海边
Recording the words I want to say to you
录下我想要对你说的话
But you won't hear them
可是你不会听见了
November 2nd, 2006
二六年十一月二日
Do you know where I am?
你知道我在哪里吗？
Please choose which service you require
请选择服务项目
Please choose the amount of cash
请选择定额提款键
Your transaction is in progress, please wait
交易处理中，请稍候
Please take your card
请取出晶片金融卡
Your receipt is being printed, please wait
明细表列印中，请稍候
Please take your receipt
请取回交易明细表
Your account is now overdrawn
帐户可用余额不足
Thank you using this service
谢谢您的惠顾
Please come again
欢迎再次光临
Please insert your card later
请稍后插卡
Yazhu...
雅竺
Listen...
你听
This is the sound of the southernmost point
这是最南端的声音
There's still a lot I'd like to say to you
我还有好多话想要跟你说
But...
可是
I think...
我想
I will end...
我要在这里
...the recording of "Sounds of Formosa" here
结束福尔摩沙之音的录音了
It takes the most distant course
这是最最遥远的路程
To come nearest to yourself
来到最接近你的地方
And the training is at its most intricate
这是最最复杂的训练
When it leads to the utter simplicity of a tune.
引向曲调绝对的单纯
We have to knock at every alien door
你我须遍扣每扇远方的门
To finally come to our own
才能找到自己的门
To find ourselves
自己的人
It takes the most distant course
这是最最遥远的路程
To come nearest to yourself,
来到最接近你的地方
Come, come, come...
来来来来来来来来来…
It takes the most distant course
这是最最遥远的路程
To arrive at the place where one started
来到以前出发的地方
It is the final climb
这是最后一个上坡
To arrive at absolute pastoral beauty
引向田园绝对的美丽
We have to go through each illusory dream
你我须穿透每场虚幻的梦
To finally come to our own door,
最后走进自己的门
To our own field
自己的田
It takes the most distant course
这是最最遥远的路程
To come nearest to yourself.
来到最接近你的地方
To arrive at the place one misses most.
来到最最思念的地方